Guide to the Arthur Davison Ficke Papers
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
Ficke kept several scrapbooks spanning the years 1902-40. The first two contain memorabilia from his days at Harvard, including clippings of his writings from the Harvard Advocate, dinner programs, and dance cards. The scrapbooks for 1907-15 contain clippings of published poems, notices of Ficke's plays and books, and reviews. Other scrapbooks contain the author's writings for Esquire (with the exception of the "Mrs. Morton" series), articles on Asian art, and a group of articles written during 1938-39, gathered under the title "Fables of Angels and Animals."
In 1939 Ficke underwent psychoanalysis with Dr. Karl Menninger, during which he kept notes relating to it and to his state of mind. A folder of material relating to John Cowper Powys concerns an agreement made between the two for the purchase of a house in New York. Two folders concerning Edna St. Vincent Millay contain clippings and an unused draft of a contract between Millay and Harper and Brothers relating to the company's acquisition of the rights to "Renascence" and other works.
The section of Personal Papers devoted to Ficke's military career includes awards and citations, his commission, identity papers, orders, and discharge. Other material includes diplomas from Davenport High School, Harvard University, certificate of admission to the Supreme Court of Iowa, marriage announcements, divorce papers, a marriage contract, a list of medications, a will, and a folder of obituaries.
A small group of papers relate to Gladys Brown Ficke. Several folders contain clippings collected by her between 1941 and 1962. There are two diaries dated 1917 and 1924. The later one chronicles the Ficke's riding holiday in France.
Material relating to the Ficke family includes Evelyn Blunt Ficke's diaries of her 1917 and 1920 trips to China and Japan, Frances Davison Ficke's will, and genealogical information concerning the family.
Series V, Business and Legal Papers, consists of business and legal papers relating to Arthur Davison Ficke, Gladys Brown Ficke, and the Ficke family. The series contains a large section of correspondence and notes relating to Ficke's battle, in 1926, to obtain compensation from the Veterans Administration for his tuberculosis, which he believed was a result of his military service. There is also a file pertaining to Ficke's medical expenses during his final illness.
Another section concerns an income tax suit. The Internal Revenue Service questioned monetary gifts Ficke made to his wife prior to his death. This section contains correspondence, ledgers, income tax returns, and other material relating to the Ficke's finances and grouped together by Gladys Brown Ficke for use in the law suit. The outcome is not known. Of particular interest is a statement made by Dr. Karl Menninger, dated January 1948, concerning Ficke's state of mind prior to his death.
Other material includes correspondence concerning investments between the years 1917-37, checkbook statements from 1944-45, investment statements for 1931-46, income tax returns not needed for the Internal Revenue Service dispute, balance sheets, and correspondence relating to the estate of Charles August Ficke.
Series VI, Arthur Davison Ficke Foundation, consists of three boxes of correspondence, notes, and writings concerning the Foundation, from the years 1946-70. Several folders of correspondence chronicle the development of the foundation. Initially Gladys Brown Ficke thought to make her home, Hardhack, a memorial to her late husband. Later she wanted to use Hardhack as a summer artists colony at which a resident psychiatrist could study the creative process. During 1949 Gladys Brown Ficke enlisted the assistance of Dr. Lawrence Kubie in setting up a foundation to support this goal. Much of the 1949 correspondence concerns possible meeting dates for the directors of the foundation, the development a philosophy for the foundation, and possible funding sources. The Arthur Davison Ficke Foundation held its first meeting in New York City on December 9, 1949, sponsoring a conference on scientific investigation of the creative process.
In 1950 Gladys Brown Ficke decided to focus on creativity in children and corresponded with Kubie and other psychiatrists concerning research methodology. There is little correspondence after 1951. Other material includes bills and receipts, minutes of meetings, and organizational records.
The section devoted to writings contains articles on the creative process collected by Gladys Brown Ficke. There are also three articles written by her, including "A Technique for the Study of the Process of Painting in Children," which was published as a monograph in 1964.
Series VII, Artwork, consists of one box of artwork by Arthur Davison Ficke and others. Ficke is represented by 37 works of watercolor and ink on paper. Many of the works include holograph poems such as "Cytherea," "Portrait of Edna St. Vincent Millay," and "Study in Japanese Imperial Heraldry and Color." Gladys Brown Ficke is represented by an undated folder of sketches. Also included is a group of undated etchings, and a lithograph by Eric Lundgren, and a watercolor inscribed to Arthur Davison Ficke by Mary Aldis.
American poetry -- 20th Century; Art, Japanese; Creative ability in children; Divorce; Literary forgeries and mystifications; Modernism (Literature); Prints, Japanese; Psychoanalysis; Sanatoriums -- United States; Tuberculosis; World War, 1914-1918; Davenport (Iowa); East Asia -- Description and travel; Europe -- Description and travel; Photographs; Adams, Ansel, 1902-1984; Anderson, Sherwood, 1876-1941; Benét, William Rose, 1886-1950; Browne, Maurice, 1881-1955; Bynner, Witter, 1881-1968; Dell, Floyd, 1887-1969; Dreiser, Theodore, 1871-1945; Eastman, Max, 1883-1969; Ficke, Arthur Davison, 1883-1945; Ficke, Gladys; Gregory, Alyse, 1884-1967; Jeffers, Robinson, 1887-1962; Kubie, Lawrence S. (Lawrence Schlesinger), 1896-1973; Lewis, Sinclair, 1885-1951; Masters, Edgar Lee, 1868-1950; Mencken, H. L. (Henry Louis), 1880-1956; Millay, Edna St. Vincent, 1892-1950; Powys, John Cowper, 1872-1963; Powys, Llewelyn, 1884-1939; Robinson, Edwin Arlington, 1869-1935; Roosevelt, Franklin D. (Franklin Delano), 1882-1945; Santayana, George, 1863-1952; Sinclair, Upton, 1878-1968; Stamos, Theodoros, 1922-1997; Taylor, Deems, 1885-1966; Van Vechten, Carl, 1880-1964; Wheelock, John Hall, 1886-1978; Arthur Davison Ficke Foundation; Harvard University. Class of 1904
- Correspondence, 1886-1971; Series I; 7.5; (19 boxes)
  Scope and Contents
  Series I, Correspondence, is organized into three subseries: Arthur Davison Ficke Correspondence, Gladys Brown Ficke Correspondence, and Third Party Correspondence. Each subseries is arranged alphabetically by last name. In the first two subseries, letters from correspondents not listed individually may be found in "letter" general files; unidentified correspondence is arranged at the end of each subseries.
  - ARTHUR DAVISON FICKE CORRESPONDENCE
    - "A" general, 1930, 1932 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Aldis, Mary Reynolds, 1931, 1939, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Anderson, Margaret C., 1914 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Anderson, Sherwood, 1914-43 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Austin, Mary Hunter, 1930 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - "B" general, 1931-45 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Bacon, Leonard, 1924, 1942 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Benét, William Rose, 1924-36 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Blunt, Stanhope English and Fanny S., 1917, 1922 (Box 1, Folder 9-10)
    - Brown, Alice, 1940 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - Browne, Ellen Van Volkenburg, 1921, 1943 (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - Browne, Lewis, 1927, 1942 (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - Browne, Maurice, 1922-45 (Box 1, Folder 14-16)
    - Buck, Pearl, 1937-38 (Box 1, Folder 17)
    - Bynner, Witter, 1904-45 (Box 1, Folder 18-32)
    - Bynner, Witter (transcripts), 1922-45 (Box 1, Folder 33-34)
    - "C" general, 1939-40 (Box 2, Folder 35)
    - C. T. Loo and Company, 1945 (Box 2, Folder 36)
    - Canby, Henry Seidel, 1929 (Box 2, Folder 37)
    - Carman, Bliss, 1927-29 (Box 2, Folder 38)
    - Chapman, John Jay, 1929 (Box 2, Folder 39)
    - Clapp, Frederick Mortimer and Maude, 1943 (Box 2, Folder 40)
    - Coblentz, Stanton Arthur, 1942-45 (Box 2, Folder 41)
    - Colony, Horatio, 1935 (Box 2, Folder 42)
    - Cook, George Cram, 1911 (Box 2, Folder 43)
    - "D" general, 1927-40 (Box 2, Folder 44)
    - Darling, Chester Coburn, 1933 (Box 2, Folder 45)
    - Darrow, Clarence Seward, 1932 (Box 2, Folder 46)
    - Dasburg, Andrew, 1929 (Box 2, Folder 47)
    - Davison, Ella, 1929 (Box 2, Folder 48)
    - De Armand, Louis, 1924-71, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 49-50)
    - Dell, Floyd, 1917-45 (Box 2, Folder 51-61)
    - Dell, Floyd (extracts and transcripts), 1913-45 (Box 2, Folder 62)
    - Devoe, Alan, 1943-45 (Box 2, Folder 63-66)
    - Dos Passos, John, 1937 (Box 2, Folder 67)
    - Dreiser, Theodore, 1913-44 (Box 2, Folder 68-69)
    - "E" general, 1936, 1945 (Box 2, Folder 70)
    - Earle, Ferdinand, 1912 (Box 2, Folder 71)
    - Eastman, Max, 1932-42 (Box 2, Folder 72)
    - Eilshemius, Louis Michael, 1924 (Box 2, Folder 73)
    - Evans, Donald (fragment, also includes transcript of diary, 1904), 1920 (Box 2, Folder 74)
    - Evans, Florence Wilkinson, 1933 (Box 2, Folder 75)
    - "F" general, 1957, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 76)
    - Ficke, Charles August, 1927-31 (Box 3, Folder 77)
    - Ficke, Charles August and Frances, 1895-24 (Box 3, Folder 78-128)
    - Ficke, Charles August and Frances, 1924 (Box 4, Folder 129)
    - Ficke, Evelyn Blunt, 1917-45 (Box 4, Folder 130-150)
    - Ficke, Evelyn Blunt (transcripts), 1917-18 (Box 4, Folder 151)
    - Ficke, Frances, 1917-45 (Box 4, Folder 152-156)
    - Ficke, Gladys Brown, 1921 (Box 4, Folder 157)
    - Ficke, Gladys Brown, 1921-22 (Box 5, Folder 158-179)
    - Ficke, Gladys Brown, 1922 (Box 6, Folder 180-204)
    - Ficke, Gladys Brown, 1922-32 (Box 7, Folder 205-232)
    - Ficke, Gladys Brown, 1932-45 (Box 8, Folder 233-243)
    - Ficke, Jane Jonson, 1942-45 (Box 8, Folder 244)
    - Ficke, Sally Stevens, 1939, 1945 (Box 8, Folder 245)
    - Ficke, Stanhope Blunt, 1923-45 (Box 8, Folder 246-264)
    - Ficke, Stanhope Blunt (transcripts), 1939-44 (Box 8, Folder 265)
    - Field, Sara Bard, 1937 (Box 8, Folder 266)
    - Flaccus, W. Kimball, 1940 (Box 8, Folder 267)
    - Flanner, Hildegarde, 1921 (Box 8, Folder 268)
    - Franke, Katherine, 1930 (Box 8, Folder 269)
    - Franke, Kuno, 1916-30 (Box 9, Folder 270-272)
    - Freeman, Joseph, 1938-41 (Box 9, Folder 273)
    - Fuller, Helen S. and Robert, 1907 (Box 9, Folder 274)
    - "G" general, 1929-40 (Box 9, Folder 275)
    - Garland, Hamlin, 1931 (Box 9, Folder 276)
    - Glaspell, Susan, n.d. (Box 9, Folder 277)
    - Gookin, Frederick William, 1926 (Box 9, Folder 278)
    - Grant, Robert, 1927 (Box 9, Folder 279)
    - Gregory, Alyse, 1932-45 (Box 9, Folder 280-283)
    - [EMPTY FOLDER] (Box 9, Folder 284)
    - "H" general, 1923-39 (Box 9, Folder 285)
    - Hughes, Langston, 1927 (Box 9, Folder 286)
    - Hunt, Robert, 1944 (Box 9, Folder 287)
    - "J" general, 1948, n.d. (Box 9, Folder 288)
    - Jeffers, Robinson, 1929-39 (Box 9, Folder 289)
    - Jeliffe, Belinda J., 1936-45 (Box 9, Folder 290-291)
    - "K" general, 1939 (Box 9, Folder 292)
    - Koch, Muriel Langley, 1939-49 (Box 9, Folder 293-294)
    - Ledoux, Jean, 1942 (Box 9, Folder 295)
    - Ledoux, Louis Vernon, 1915-43 (Box 9, Folder 296-298)
    - Lenz, Maurice, 1945 (Box 9, Folder 299)
    - Leonard, William Ellery, 1923 (Box 9, Folder 300)
    - Lewis, Sinclair, 1934-44 (Box 9, Folder 301)
    - Lin, Yu-t'ang, 1943 (Box 9, Folder 302)
    - Lindbergh, Anne Morrow, 1941 (Box 9, Folder 303)
    - Lindsay, Vachel (transcript), 1913 (Box 9, Folder 304)
    - Lundgren, Eric, 1937-44, n.d. (Box 9, Folder 305-312)
    - Lundgren, Eric (transcripts), 1939-42 (Box 9, Folder 313)
    - "M" general, 1932-40, n.d. (Box 9, Folder 314)
    - Mason, Daniel Gregory, 1942 (Box 9, Folder 315)
    - Masters, Edgar Lee, 1915-37 (Box 9, Folder 316-18)
    - Masters, Edgar Lee, 1937-45 (Box 10, Folder 319-28)
    - Mencken, H. L., 1922-43, n.d. (Box 10, Folder 329)
    - Menninger, Karl A., 1943, 1945 (Box 10, Folder 330)
    - Merkel, Otto Julius, 1941 (Box 10, Folder 331)
    - Metzgar, Judson D., 1905-45 (Box 10, Folder 332-41)
    - Metzgar, Judson D. (transcripts), 1910-37 (Box 10, Folder 342)
    - Millay, Edna St. Vincent, 1912-22 (Box 10, Folder 343-348)
    - Millay, Edna St.Vincent (transcripts), 1918-45 (Box 10, Folder 349)
    - Millay, Edna St. Vincent and Eugen Boissevain, 1924-25 (Box 10, Folder 350-351)
    - Millay, Edna St. Vincent and Eugen Boissevain, 1932-45 (Box 11, Folder 352-368)
    - Millay, Edna St. Vincent and Eugen Boissevain (transcripts), 1912-27 (Box 11, Folder 369-370)
    - Miller, Alice Duer, 1939 (Box 11, Folder 371)
    - More, Paul Elmer, 1930 (Box 11, Folder 372)
    - Morton, David, 1939 (Box 11, Folder 373)
    - New York Herald Tribune, 1940, 1945 (Box 11, Folder 374)
    - "O" general, 1919, 1935 (Box 11, Folder 375)
    - O'Neil, Nance, 1939 (Box 11, Folder 376)
    - O'Neill, Rose Cecil, 1916-18 (Box 11, Folder 377-378)
    - O'Neill, Rose Cecil, 1921-45 (Box 12, Folder 379)
    - "P" general, 1922-42 (Box 12, Folder 380)
    - Page, Curtis Hidden, 1924-40 (Box 12, Folder 381-382)
    - Phillpotts, Eden, 1939-42 (Box 12, Folder 383)
    - Phipps, Katherine, 1935 (Box 12, Folder 384)
    - Powys, John Cowper, 1915-45 (Box 12, Folder 385-410)
      For arrowheads related to the letter dated 1932 May 17, see: Box 45, folder 1426a
    - Powys, John Cowper (transcripts), 1939-45 (Box 12, Folder 411)
    - Powys, Llewelyn, 1923-35 (Box 12, Folder 412-416)
    - Powys, Llewelyn, 1936-39 (Box 13, Folder 417-420)
    - Powys, Llewelyn (transcripts), 1923-39 (Box 13, Folder 421)
    - Plutzik, Hyam, 1941 (Box 13, Folder 422)
    - Pringle, [John C.], 1934-45 (Box 13, Folder 423-424)
    - Pringle, [John C.] (transcripts), 1938-41 (Box 13, Folder 425)
    - "R" general, 1918-38 (Box 13, Folder 426)
    - Robinson, Edward Arlington, 1921-30 (Box 13, Folder 427)
    - Roosevelt, Franklin Delano, 1903-43 (Box 13, Folder 428)
    - Rowley, Nelson, 1934-45 (Box 13, Folder 429-436)
    - "S" general, 1918-45 (Box 13, Folder 437)
    - Santayana, George, 1910-39 (Box 13, Folder 438)
    - Seiffert, Marjorie Allen, 1917-39 (Box 13, Folder 439-443)
    - Simonson, Alice Ficke, 1901-45 (Box 13, Folder 444)
    - Sinclair, Upton, 1914-28 (Box 13, Folder 445)
    - Sloan, John, 1945 (Box 13, Folder 446)
    - "T" general, 1945, 1947 (Box 13, Folder 447)
    - Taylor, Deems, 1927-43 (Box 13, Folder 448)
    - Thomson, Raymond L., 1944 (Box 13, Folder 449)
    - Torrence, Ridgely, 1936-45 (Box 13, Folder 450)
    - "U" general, 1932 (Box 13, Folder 451)
    - "V" general, 1929, 1945 (Box 13, Folder 452)
    - Van Vechten, Carl, 1921-24 (Box 13, Folder 453-455)
    - Van Vechten, Carl, 1925-45, n.d. (Box 14, Folder 456-468)
    - "W" general, 1927-45 (Box 14, Folder 469)
    - Watzek, Helene Ficke, 1936-45 (Box 14, Folder 470)
    - Wheelock, John Hall, 1914-45 (Box 14, Folder 471)
    - Wilstach, John, 1936-42, n.d. (Box 14, Folder 472-474)
    - Wolff, Dr. H. G., 1938 (Box 14, Folder 475)
    - Wood, Charles Erskine Scott, 1937 (Box 14, Folder 476)
    - Wood, Clement, 1936 (Box 14, Folder 477)
    - Wylie, Elinor, 1925-26 (Box 14, Folder 478)
    - Young, Carl, 1939-42 (Box 14, Folder 479)
    - Zimbalist, Efram, 1938, n.d. (Box 14, Folder 480)
    - Unidentified, 1922-40 (Box 14, Folder 481)
  - GLADYS BROWN FICKE CORRESPONDENCE
    - "A" general, 1952, 1961 (Box 15, Folder 482)
    - Adams, Mr. and Mrs. Franklin Pierce, 1945-46 (Box 15, Folder 483)
    - Benét, William Rose, 1945 (Box 15, Folder 484)
    - Boissevain, Eugen, 1947, n.d. (Box 15, Folder 485)
    - Brown, Wolsten Crocker, 1958 (Box 15, Folder 486)
    - Browne, Ellen Von Volkenburg, 1945, 1948 (Box 15, Folder 487)
    - Browne, Maurice, 1935-54 (Box 15, Folder 488-490)
    - Bynner, Witter, 1944-64 (Box 15, Folder 491-512)
    - "C" general, 1946-70, n.d. (Box 15, Folder 513)
    - C. T. Loo and Company, 1945, 1952 (Box 15, Folder 514)
    - Clapp, Frederick Mortimer, 1945-63 (Box 16, Folder 515-520)
    - Coblentz, Stanton A., 1947 (Box 16, Folder 521)
    - Colin, Ralph, 1951, 1960 (Box 16, Folder 522)
    - "D" general, 1969, n.d. (Box 16, Folder 523)
    - Devoe, Alan, 1945-51 (Box 16, Folder 524)
    - De Mille, Agnes, 1945-58 (Box 16, Folder 525)
    - Dell, B. Marie, 1945 (Box 16, Folder 526)
    - Dell, Floyd, 1946-53 (Box 16, Folder 527-528)
    - Dodd, Mead, and Company, Inc., 1969 (Box 16, Folder 529)
    - Doubleday and Company, Inc., 1954 (Box 16, Folder 530)
    - "E" general, 1949-56 (Box 16, Folder 531)
    - Ellis, Norma Millay, 1950-53 (Box 16, Folder 532)
    - "F" general, 1945-46 (Box 16, Folder 533)
    - Ficke, Charles August and Frances, 1924, n.d. (Box 16, Folder 534)
    - Ficke, Stanhope Blunt, 1945-62, n.d. (Box 16, Folder 535-536)
    - Flaccus, Kimball, 1952-53 (Box 16, Folder 537)
    - Freeman, Joseph, 1945 (Box 16, Folder 538)
    - "G" general, 1947-67 (Box 16, Folder 539)
    - Gallup, Donald, 1968, 1970 (Box 16, Folder 540)
    - Gould, Jean, 1968 (Box 16, Folder 541)
    - Gregory, Alyse, 1945-63 (Box 16, Folder 542-547)
    - Gysin, Brion, 1945-68 (Box 16, Folder 548)
    - "H" general, 1945-68 (Box 16, Folder 549)
    - Harper and Brothers, 1952 (Box 16, Folder 550)
    - Harvard University, 1945-48 (Box 16, Folder 551)
    - "J" general, 1932-46 (Box 16, Folder 552)
    - Jeliffe, Belinda J., 1945-55, n.d. (Box 16, Folder 553-555)
    - Koch, Muriel Langley, 1945, 1949 (Box 16, Folder 556)
    - Kubie, Lawrence S., 1950-61 (Box 16, Folder 557-558)
    - "L" general, 1945-52 (Box 16, Folder 559)
    - Lamont, Corliss, 1946, 1962 (Box 16, Folder 560)
    - Ledoux, Louis Vernon, 1945, 1952 (Box 17, Folder 561)
    - Lundgren, Eric, 1947-64 (Box 17, Folder 562-566)
    - "M" general, 1945-71 (Box 17, Folder 567)
    - MacDougall, Alan Ross, 1952 (Box 17, Folder 568)
    - Masters, Edgar Lee, 1945 (Box 17, Folder 569)
    - Masters, Ellen, 1950-51 (Box 17, Folder 570)
    - Menninger, Karl A., 1946 (Box 17, Folder 571)
    - Merkel, Otto Julius, 1938-55 (Box 17, Folder 572-574)
    - Metzgar, Judson D., 1946-57 (Box 17, Folder 575)
    - Millay, Edna St. Vincent, 1922-45 (Box 17, Folder 576)
    - "N" general, 1945, 1949, n.d. (Box 17, Folder 577)
    - "P" general, 1946-62 (Box 17, Folder 578)
    - Phipps, Elizabeth, n.d. (Box 17, Folder 579)
    - Phipps, Katherine, 1934-52 (Box 17, Folder 580-582)
    - Playter, Phyllis, 1957-63 (Box 17, Folder 583-584)
    - Powys, John Cowper, 1930-60 (Box 17, Folder 585-590)
    - Price, Robert, 1949 (Box 17, Folder 591)
    - Pringle, [John C.], 1945-46 (Box 17, Folder 592)
    - Quinn, James J., 1948-54 (Box 17, Folder 593)
    - "R" general, 1959-71 (Box 17, Folder 594)
    - Rapaport, David, 1958 (Box 17, Folder 595)
    - "S" general, 1945-68 (Box 17, Folder 596)
    - Seiffert, Marjorie, 1961-62 (Box 17, Folder 597)
    - Siberell, Lloyd Emerson, 1945, 1947 (Box 17, Folder 598)
    - Simonson, Alice Ficke, 1945-52 (Box 17, Folder 599)
    - Smith, William Jay, 1958-59 (Box 17, Folder 600)
    - Stamos, Theodore, 1949-56 (Box 17, Folder 601)
    - Stowe, Lyman Beecher, 1945 (Box 17, Folder 602)
    - "T" general, 1959-63 (Box 17, Folder 603)
    - Torrence, Ridgely, 1945-52 (Box 17, Folder 604)
    - "U" general, 1958 (Box 17, Folder 605)
    - "V" general, 1957 (Box 18, Folder 606)
    - Van Vechten, Carl, 1931-54 (Box 18, Folder 607-613)
    - "W" general, 1945-71 (Box 18, Folder 614)
    - Watzek, Helene Ficke, 1945-51 (Box 18, Folder 615)
    - Wheelock, John Hall, 1945 (Box 18, Folder 616)
    - Williams, William Carlos, 1951 (Box 18, Folder 617)
    - Wood, Clement, 1940 (Box 18, Folder 618)
    - "Y" general, 1945 (Box 18, Folder 619)
    - Yale University, 1957 (Box 18, Folder 620)
    - Unidentified, 1949-68, n.d. (Box 18, Folder 621)
  - THIRD PARTY CORRESPONDENCE
    - Davison, Ella to Charles August and Frances Ficke, 1886 (Box 19, Folder 622)
    - Davison, [Mammie] to Charles August and Frances Ficke, 1886 (Box 19, Folder 623)
    - Ficke, Evelyn Blunt to
      - Stanhope English and Fanny S. Blunt, 1908-21 (Box 19, Folder 624-628)
      - Stanhope English and Fanny S. Blunt (transcripts), 1920-21 (Box 19, Folder 629)
      - Charles August and Frances Ficke, 1908 (Box 19, Folder 630)
    - Ficke, Stanhope Blunt to Stanhope English and Fanny S. Blunt, 1920 (Box 19, Folder 631)
    - Flaccus, W. Kimball to John Cowper Powys, 1962 (Box 19, Folder 632)
    - Fuller, Robert to [Charles August Ficke?], 1911 (Box 19, Folder 633)
    - Galarowicz, Zegmant to Edna St. Vincent Millay, 1930 (Box 19, Folder 634)
    - Goldschmidt, Jules W. to Edna St. Vincent Millay, 1934
    - Iowa State Library to Charles August Ficke, 1917 (Box 19, Folder 635)
    - Powys, John Cowper to Mary Aldis, 1933-34 (Box 19, Folder 636)
    - Schrock, J. N. to Edna St. Vincent Millay, 1930 (Box 19, Folder 637)
    - Smith, Kitty to Witter Bynner, 1946 (Box 19, Folder 638)
    - Volka, [E.?] to Mary Aldis, 1921 (Box 19, Folder 639)
    - Wong, V. S. to Evelyn Blunt Ficke, 1920 (Box 19, Folder 640)
    - Unidentified to Maurice Brown, [1938] (Box 19, Folder 641)
- Writings, 1895-1959; Series II; 9.75; (25 boxes)
  Series II, Writings, is organized into three subseries: Arthur Davison Ficke, Gladys Brown Ficke, and Writings of Others. The first two subseries are arranged alphabetically by type of material; the last subseries is arranged alphabetically by author.
  - ARTHUR DAVISON FICKE
    - Novels
      - "The Blue Jade Sceptre"
        - Part I-III, chapters 1-37, typescript, corrected, second draft, 1940 Jul-Aug (Box 20, Folder 642-650)
        - Chapters 1-28, typescript, carbon, corrected, third draft, 1940 Sep (Box 20, Folder 651-657)
        - Chapters 1-19, typescript, carbon, corrected, fourth draft, 1940 Nov (Box 20, Folder 658-663)
        - Chapters 20-25, typescript, carbon, corrected, fourth draft, 1940 Nov (Box 21, Folder 664-665)
        - Chapter 26, typescript, original, corrected, final draft, 1941 Jan (Box 21, Folder 666-674)
        - Artwork, n.d. (Box 21, Folder 675)
        - Correspondence, 1940-41, n.d. (Box 21, Folder 676)
        - Notes, 1940-41, n.d. (Box 21, Folder 677-678)
        - Postcards, n.d. (Box 21, Folder 679)
      - "The Daughter of Dr. Hawmer": outline and [Chapter 1?]: holograph and typescript, with notes (Box 21, Folder 680)
      - "The Filling Station": outline and notes, holograph (Box 21, Folder 681)
      - "It was to Buy Two Black Horses": Chapter 1, typescript, original, corrected, 1942 (Box 21, Folder 682)
      - "The Man Who Bought the Monkey": holograph and typescript, original, with notes, [ca. 1936] (Box 21, Folder 683)
      - "The Mirror of the Huntress" ["Portraits of Cecile Marion Holland"]: notes, holograph, and typescript, corrected, 1914-40 (Box 21, Folder 684)
      - Mrs. Morton of Mexico
        - Introductory notes, table of contents, and list of possible titles: typescript, original, [first revised draft], 1939 (Box 21, Folder 685)
        - Chapters 1-2, 4-5: first revised draft, typescript, original and carbon, corrected, 1939 (Box 21, Folder 686-690)
        - Omitted epilogue: typescript, carbon, first revised draft, 1939 (Box 21, Folder 691)
        - Omitted chapter: typescript, original, corrected, first revised draft, 1939 (Box 21, Folder 692)
        - Chapter 1 and 5: second revised draft, typescript, carbon, corrected, 1939 (Box 21, Folder 693-694)
        - Chapter 5: third revised draft, typescript, carbon, corrected, 1939 (Box 22, Folder 695)